The interface is pretty simple.
L'interface est simple.
You put your horizontal X-coordinate here, vertical Y-coordinate here.
Tu mets la coordonnée X ici et la coordonnée Y là.
When you're happy with those, press this button.
Quand tu es prête, appuie sur cette touche.
Got it.
Pigé.
Leonard, you'll never guess who ljust found online. Hey.
Leonard, devine qui j'ai trouvé en ligne ?
-Nice shot. -Eh, his giant head did most of the work.
Joli tir.
Very mature. You're lucky I'm out of Silly String.
Très adulte. Vous avez du pot, je n'ai pas de bombe a serpentins.
As I was saying, Leonard, you'll never guess who I just found online.
Tu ne devineras jamais qui j'ai trouvé en ligne.
-Professor Proton. -You're kidding.
- Le professeur Proton. - Tu plaisantes !
-He's still alive? -Yes.
- Il vit toujours ? -Oui.
-Who's Professor Proton? -He was the host of this great-- Hey.
- Qui est le professeur Proton ? - C'était l'invité de...
Professor Proton hosted my favorite science show when l was a child.
Il présentait mon émission scientifique préférée.
I never missed an episode.
Je ne la ratais jamais.
He demonstrated scientific principles using everyday objects.
Il démontrait des principes scientifiques
It was pretty cool.
C‘était cool.
Aw. It's so cute when you use the word "cool" wrong.
J‘adore quand tu utilises mal le mot ”cool".
Like when kids say "pasghetti."
Comme quand les gamins disent "pasghetti".
Oh, dear Lord. Leonard, look.
Mon Dieu. Leonard, regarde.
He's still available for parties and events.
Il fait des fêtes et des spectacles.
-We should hire him. -Hire him to do what?
- Engageons-le. - Pour faire quoi ?
Whatever we want. Hang out, do experiments...
Passer du temps, faire des expériences,
...make him take 12 pictures with us so we can make a calendar.
lui faire prendre 12 photos avec nous pour un calendrier.
It would be awesome to hang out with him. I just used "awesome" wrong, didn't I?
Ce serait génial de passer du temps avec lui. J'ai mal utilisé ”génial" ?
Well, I'm e-mailing him right now.
Je lui envoie un e-mail.
-Do you remember his old theme song? -Of course I do.
- Tu te rappelles la chanson ? - Bien sûr.
Hey, uh, ljust found out I have to be at the telescope lab all weekend.
Je dois passer tout le week—end au centre astronomique.
Any chance you and Bernadette could take care of my dog?
Bernadette et toi pourriez vous occuper de ma chienne ?
-Why don't you put her in a kennel? -Why don't you put your mother in a home?
- Mets-Ia dans un chenil. - Mets ta mère dans un asile.
To be honest, she'd do better in the kennel.
Elle serait mieux dans un chenil.
-l'll talk to Bernie. I'm sure it's fine. -Thank you.
- Bernie sera d‘accord. - Merci.
It's happening. Leonard, it's happening.
Leonard, c‘est bon.
Professor Proton is coming to our house.
Le professeur Proton Vient chez nous.
You mean the guy who used to host that lame kids show?
Le type qui présentait cette émission nulle pour gamins ?
And you just got yourself uninvited.
Tu ne seras pas invité.
See, I told you I'd find a tactful way to do that.
Je t‘avais dit que je ferais preuve de tact.
-How'd you get him to come to your house? -As Professor Proton always says:
Comment vous avez réussi ale faire venir ?
"There is no problem you can't solve if you use your noggin."
”Tout problème peut être résolu en utilisant sa caboche."
-And he wrote him a check. -Yeah, that too. Big check.
- Il lui a écrit un chèque. - Un gros chèque.
Uncle Howard.
Oncle Howard.
Cinnamon's here for her sleepover party.
Cannelle est la pour faire dodo.
You know if you had a stroke, she'd eat you, right?
Si tu avais une attaque, elle te boufferait.
And it would be my pleasure to be her num-num.
J'en serais ravi.
Okay, so, what do I need to know to take care of her?
Qu‘est—ce qu'il faut que je fasse ?
It's very simple.
C‘est trés simple.
For breakfast, she has an egg white frittata.
Le matin, elle mange une omelette.
Give her a choice of home fries or an English muffin.
Tu lui proposes des frites ou un muffin.
But not both. We're watching our weight.
Pas les deux. On surveille son poids.
Uh, for dinner, something simple, a veal chop...
Le soir, une côtelette de veau ou des scampi.
-Classy dog. -Yes.
- La classe. - Oui.
Also, don't forget to close the toilet or she'll drink out of it.
Ferme le couvercle des toilettes, sinon elle boit dedans.
I feel for you. Heh.
Je compatis.
I've got a psychotic mommy too.
Moi aussi,j'ai une mère psychotique.
SHELDON: Leonard, are you in bed?
Leonard, tu es couché ?
Great.
Super.
SHELDON: I can't sleep.
Je n'arrive pas a dormir.
Well, I can, so shut up.
Moi, si. Alors ferme—la.
SHELDON: Do you realize that in less than nine hours, Arthur Jeffries...
Dans moins de neuf heures, Arthur Jeffries,
...a.k.a. Professor Proton, will be in our apartment?
alias Professeur Proton, sera chez nous ?
You know if you stay up all night, you're going to be sleepy tomorrow.
Si tu restes debout toute la nuit, tu seras fatigué demain.
And a sleepy Sheldon is a cranky Sheldon. And a cranky Sheldon...
Donc tu seras grincheux. Et quand tu es grincheux,
...is actually no different than a regular Sheldon. Good night.
en fait, tu es dans ton état normal. Bonne nuit.
SHELDON: I'm thinking of wearing a tuxedo.
Je porterais bien un smoking.
That's not ridiculous. Good night.
Ce n‘est pas une idée ridicule. Bonne nuit.
SHELDON: Do you have cufflinks?
Tu as des boutons de manchette ?
-No. -Just as well.
- Non. - Peu importe.
Where can you rent a tuxedo at 3:00 in the morning?
Où loue-t-on un smoking a 3 h du matin ?
Okay. Good night.
Bonne nuit.
SHELDON: Nice to meet you, Professor Proton.
Enchanté, Professeur Proton.
Nice to meet you, Profe--
Enchanté, Prof…
What?
Quoi ?
SHELDON: I still can't sleep.
Je n'arrive toujours pas a dormir.
She really, uh, tuckered herself out at the park, huh?
Elle s‘est épuisée au parc.
Yeah. You two were so cute playing together.
Vous étiez mignons ajouer ensemble.
It was kind of fun throwing a ball and not having anyone laugh at me.
C‘était amusant de lui lancer une balle
And you were sweet not to throw it too far so she didn't wear out her tiny legs.
C‘était gentil de l‘envoyer tout près pour éviter qu'elle se fatigue.
Heh, yeah, that's what I was doing.
C‘était l‘effet recherché.
There were a few moments today when I felt like we were a little family.
J'ai eu l'impression qu'on formait une famille aujourd'hui.
-Really? -Yeah.
- C‘est vrai ? - Oui.
I never thought of myself as a mom, but when we were out...
Je ne me voyais pas maman, mais en étant tous les trois,
...I felt like someday we could do it.
j'ai eu l'impression que ça pouvait arriver.
Of course we can.
Bien sûr.
Especially if our baby's as calm and quiet as little Cinnam--
Surtout si notre bébé est aussi calme que Cann..
Son of a bitch, she's gone!
Merde, elle n‘est plus la.
-Well, where'd she go? -I don't know. She didn't leave a note.
- Où est-elie ? - Elle n‘a pas laissé de mot.
You were supposed to put her back in the stroller.
Tu devais la mettre dans la poussette.
-No, I wasn't. You were. -No, I wasn't.
- Non, c‘était toi. - Non.
-Yes, you were. -Yeah, well, you throw like a girl.
- Si. - Tu lances la halle comme une fille.
I'm getting worried.
Je suis inquiet.
Relax, Sheldon, he's only a few minutes late.
Il n‘a que quelques minutes de retard.
Professor Proton was never late when he was on TV.
Il n‘étaitjamais en retard a la télé.
You know, every day, 4:00, he was there.
Tous les jours a 16 h, il était la.
Unless tornadoes were ripping apart East Texas, then we'd join him in progress.
Sauf en cas de tornade au Texas, auquel cas on le rejoignait là:—bas.
It's him.
C‘est lui.
Hello?
Allô ?
Well, I see.
Je vois.
All right, we can come get you. Yeah, we'll see you soon.
On peut venir vous chercher. A tout de suite.
-Bye. -Where is he?
- Au revoir. - Où est-il ?
The third floor landing. The poor old guy's been walking up the stairs for half an hour.
Au 3e étage. Le pauvre monte les escaliers depuis une demi-heure.
It's really you.
C‘est vraiment vous.
Mr. Jeffries, I am so sorry.
M. Jeffries, excusez-moi.
We should have told you about the broken elevator.
On aurait dû vous dire que l‘ascenseur était en panne.
I agree.
Je suis d‘accord.
Professor Proton, it's an honor to meet you.
Professeur Proton, c‘est un honneur de vous rencontrer.
Uh, just call me Arthur.
Appelez—moi Arthur.
...did you hear that?
Tu as entendu ?
Professor Proton said I should call him Arthur.
Le professeur Proton m‘a dit de l‘appeler Arthur.
No, a friend would have told me about the elevator.
Non, un ami m'aurait prévenu pour l'ascenseur.
Look at me.
Regardez-moi.
I can get as close to you as I want without my mom saying it's going to ruin my eyes.
Je peux m‘approcher de vous
ls, uh, he dangerous?
Il est dangereux ?
Actually, he's a genius.
En fait, c‘est un génie.
That doesn't answer my question.
Ça ne répond pas a ma question.
Mr. Jeffries, I'm Leonard. This is my girlfriend, Penny.
M. Jeffries, je suis Leonard. Voici ma petite amie, Penny.
Well, I hope I haven't, uh, kept the kids waiting...
J'espère que les enfants n‘ont pas trop attendu pour le spectacle.
Oh, no, there are no kids. No, the show's for me.
Ce n‘est pas pour les enfants. C‘est pour moi.
Come on, I'll race you...
Allons-y. On fait la course...
...Arthur.
Arthur.
ARTHUR: Is the blond girl really your girlfriend?
La blonde est vraiment votre petite amie ?
LEONARD: Yes, sir. -You're the genius.
- Oui. - C‘est vous, le génie.
So do you do a lot of appearances like this?
Vous faites beaucoup de spectacles comme ça ?
It's hard to say. I'm still trying to figure out...
Difficile à dire. J'essaie encore de comprendre
...what this is.
ce qui se passe.
We just wanted to hang out with you and maybe learn a little about your life.
On voulait en savoir un peu plus sur votre vie.
Well, there really isn't too much to tell.
Il n‘y a pas grand—chose à dire.
After the TV show was canceled...
Quand l'émission a été annulée,
...nobody in the scientific world would take me seriously...
personne dans le monde scientifique ne me prenait au sérieux
...so I was forced to do these children's parties to make a living.
etj'ai dû faire des spectacles pour enfants pour gagner ma vie.
That's too bad. But still, working with kids, it must be rewarding.
Dommage. Mais c‘est enrichissant de travailler avec les enfants.
You get bit a lot.
On se fait souvent mordre.
Let me see if I have this straight.
Voyons si j'ai bien compris.
You two are physicists...
Vous êtes deux physiciens
...and you want me to do a children's science show?
et vous voulez que je fasse
And if there's time, take 12 pictures with us in seasonal clothing.
Et 12 photos avec nous en tenue de saison.
You know, I'm a real scientist.
Je suis un vrai scientifique.
l have a PhD from Cornell University.
J'ai un doctorat de l'université de Cornell.
Yeah, that's great. Did you bring your puppet?
Super. Vous avez apporté votre marionnette ?
I hate that puppet.
Je la déteste.
How could anybody hate Gino the Neutrino?
Comment peut-on détester Gino Ie Neutrino ?
It's nice, huh?
Il est mignon, non ?
I got him for 20 bucks on eBay.
Je l'ai eu pour 20 $ sur eBay.
Including the shipping.
Frais de port inclus.
I'm awake, right?
Je suis bien réveillé ?
This is happening?
Ça a vraiment lieu ?
-Cinnamon!
- Cannelle !
You know, maybe she doesn't recognize her name because of Raj's accent.
Elle doit être habituée à l'accent de Raj.
Good thinking.
Bien vu. Cannelle, Viens voir papa.
Cinnamon, where are you...
Cannelle, où es-tu, ma petite côte d'agneau ?
-Nice. Heh. -Thanks.
- Bien. - Merci.
When this all blows over, remember that voice.
Quand cette histoire sera finie, n'oublie pas cette voix.
It's kind of a turn-on. Heh.
Ça m‘excite.
It turns you on when I sound like Raj?
Ça t'excite quand j'ai la voix de Raj ?
[IN NORMAL VOICE] Cinnamon!
Cannelle !
Okay, as I put the egg on top...
Quand je mettrai l'œuf sur le dessus,
...and the flame goes out...
que la flamme sortira
...and the air pressure decreases in the flask...
et que la pression atmosphérique diminuera dans la fiole,
...what do you think will happen?
que se passera—HI ?
-l thinkl know. -lt's gonna get sucked in.
- Je crois le savoir. - Il sera aspiré.
It's going to get sucked in.
Il sera aspiré.
Okay, I didn't know.
Je ne le savais pas.
See, I'm not a scientist like them. Heh.
Je ne suis pas une scientifique.
I figured that out.
J‘avais compris.
-Potato clock. Do potato clock. -What's that?
- L‘horloge pomme de terre! - C‘est quoi ?
| power a clock with a potato.
Je fais marcher une horloge avec une pomme de terre.
Shut up. You can do that?
Vous vous fichez de moi. Vous pouvez faire ça ?
I mean, heh, wouldn't that solve the world's energy crisis?
Ça résoudrait la crise énergétique, non ?
Look, guys, keep your money. I think I'm done.
Gardez votre argent. J'ai terminé.
What's wrong? Is she upsetting you? Because I can make her go away.
Elle vous embéte ? Je peux lui dire de partir.
No, she's the only reason I've stayed this long.
Non, c‘est pour elle que je suis resté aussi longtemps.
Then what is it?
C‘est quoi, alors ?
I don't know. I think I'm just--
Je ne sais pas. Je crois que…
I just don't want to be Professor Proton anymore.
Je ne veux plus être le professeur Proton.
Well, how can you say that? Professor Proton's the best.
Comment pouvez-vous dire ça ? Le professeur Proton est le meilleur.
What has it ever gotten me?
Qu'est-ce que ça m‘a apporté ?
I mean, I'm an 83-year-old man who has potatoes in his suitcase.
Je suis un homme de 83 ans avec des patates dans sa valise.
Other scientists think I'm ajoke.
Les scientifiques me prennent pour un rigolo.
And the puppeteer who did Gino...
Le marionnettiste qui a fait Gino,
...well, he also...
il s‘est aussi...
...did my wife.
fait ma femme.
Mr. Jeffries, I need to show you something.
M. Jeffries, je veux vous montrer quelque chose.
-l'm sorry to hear about your troubles. -Uh, thanks.
- Désolée pour tous vos problèmes. - Merci.
But if you don't mind me asking, uh, the potato clock, how does it work?
Mais puis-je vous demander comment marche l‘horloge ?
Is it a trick clock or a trick potato?
C‘est une fausse horloge ou une fausse pomme de terre ?
What do you two talk about?
De quoi parlez-vous ensemble ?
I wrote a fan letter to you when l was a child in Texas...
Je vous ai écrit une lettre quand j‘étais enfant, au Texas,
...and you sent this autographed picture back to me.
et vous m'avez envoyé cette photo avec votre autographe.
Do you remember that?
Vous vous rappelez ?
I'll give you a hint. l have a bracelet with my own address on it.
Pour info,je porte un bracelet avec mon adresse dessus.
Well, anyway, um, you may find this hard to believe...
Bon. Vous aurez du mal ale croire,
...but I didn't have any friends growing up.
mais je n‘avais pas d‘ami quand j‘étais petit.
No, I get that.
Non, je le comprends.
But, um, I did have you.
Mais je vous avais, vous.
And every day at 4:00, you'd come to my house on Channel 68...
Tous les jours, a 16 h, vous veniez chez moi sur la chaîne 68
...and we'd do science together.
et on faisait des sciences ensemble.
If it hadn't been for you, well, who knows what would have become of me, you know?
Sans vous, Dieu sait ce que je serais devenu.
Instead of a world-class physicist, lcould've wound up as a hobo...
Au lieu d‘être un éminent scientifique,
...Of a surgeon.
ou chirurgien.
I bet there are important discoveries being made every day...
D‘importantes découvertes sont faites
...because you inspired millions of kids to pursue science.
car vous avez motivé des millions d‘enfants à étudier la science.
In a way, their discoveries are your discoveries.
Leurs découvertes sont les vôtres.
It's true. A generation of young scientists are standing on your shoulders.
Vous avez inspiré une génération de jeunes scientifiques.
Well, thank you, guys. That means a lot.
Merci. C‘est trés gentil.
Well, it's important you know how much you mean to us.
Il faut que vous sachiez a quel point vous étes important.
I'm having...
J'ai...
...a problem with my pacemaker.
un probléme avec mon pacemaker.
I'll call for help.
Je vais appeler de l‘aide.
Any chance we could plug it in to the potato?
On ne peut pas le brancher sur la patate ?
What do you mean you found my dog? She's with my friends.
Tu as trouvé ma chienne ? Elle est chez mes amis.
Is she okay?
Elle va bien ?
Thank you. Uh, just text me your address, I'm on my way.
Merci. Envoie—moi ton adresse, j‘arrive.
If she's hungry, go ahead and feed her but do not give her anything starchy.
Si elle a faim, donne—lui a manger, mais pas de féculents.
She's having risotto for dinner.
Elle va manger du risotto ce soir.
Your vitals are stable, but let's take you in for tests just to be safe.
On va vous emmener faire des examens, pour être sûrs.
-Want one of us to go in the ambulance? -l'll do it.
- Vous voulez qu'on l'accompagne ? - Moi !
He's not a relative, he's not allowed, right?
Il n‘est pas de ma famille, il n‘a pas le droit.
-No, it's not a rule. He can go. -Oh, yes.
- Non, il peut venir. -Oui !
I can't catch a break today.
Je n'ai pas de pot aujourd'hui.
We'll pack up your stuff, meet you at the hospital.
On vous apportera vos affaires à l‘hôpital.
Sorry things turned out this way.
Désolé que ça ait mal tourné.
Well, at this point, I'm just glad someone's carrying me down the stairs.
Je suis content qu'on me porte dans les escaliers.
Met my childhood hero, now I get to ride in an ambulance.
J'ai rencontré mon héros, je vais monter dans une ambulance.
Boy, if we can get him to do that calendar, this will be the best day ever.
S'il peut faire le calendrier, ce sera le plus beau jour de ma vie.
I can't believe we lost her.
Comment on a pu la perdre!
What was I thinking? I'd be a terrible mom.
Je serais une mère indigne.
Maybe with the first one.
Peut-être avec le premier.
But kids are like pancakes, the first one's always a throwaway.
Les enfants, c‘est comme les crêpes, la première est ratée.
-How's this look? -lt's fine.
- C‘est comment ? - Bien.
-Where'd you get that picture of her? -lt's not her. I Googled "foo-foo little dogs."
Où as-tu trouvé sa photo ?
It's Raj. Stay quiet.
C‘est Raj. Tais-toi.
Hey, heh, bad timing. Bernadette just took Cinnamon out for a walk.
Bernadette Vient d‘emmener Cannelle faire une promenade.
Interesting. Did they take a walk down Liars' Lane?
Intéressant. Elles se promènent dans l‘allée des menteurs ?
-What? -A lane frequented by liars.
Une allée fréquentée par les menteurs.
Like you, you big liar.
Comme toi, espèce de menteur.
-You have her? -Thank God she's okay.
- Tu l'as ? - Heureusement, elle va bien.
Well, I trusted you and you let me down. The poor thing's been shaking for hours.
Vous m‘avez laissé tomber.
-l'm really sorry. -Hang on, you've had her for hours?
- Pardon. - Tu l'as depuis des heures ?
Yes. I picked her up and then we both went for massages to try and calm down.
Je suis allé la chercher
And then we got Pinkberry.
Et on a mangé des glaces.
You knew she was okay and you couldn't pick up the phone to tell us?
Tu savais qu'elle allait bien et tu ne nous as pas appelés ?
-Well, I thought about-- -Don't "well" me, mister.
- Eh bien, je pensais... - Pas de ”Eh bien" !
We've been worried sick.
On était super inquiets.
She could have been dead for all we knew. You should be ashamed of yourself.
On la croyait morte. Tu devrais avoir honte.
-Sorry, I just-- -Sorry's not good enough.
- Pardon, je... - Ce n‘est pas suffisant.
Maybe you need to take some time and think about what you've done.
Réfléchis a ce que tu as fait.
Nice guilt trip. Heh. You are gonna be an amazing mom.
Super, la culpabilité. Tu seras une mère extraordinaire.
[SINGING] Soft kitty, warm kitty
Chaton tout doux et tout chaud
Little ball of fur
Petite boule de poils
Happy kitty, sleepy kitty
Chaton tout content et tout fatigué
Purr, purr, purr
Tu fais roman, roman, roman
Thank you, Sheldon. That was very nice.
Merci. C‘était très joli.
-Want me to sing it again? -No.
- Je recommence ? - Non.
The fourth time was the charm.
La quatrième édition m‘a envoûté.
There anything I can get for you? Some apple juice? Uh, some Jell-O?
Vous voulez du jus de pomme ? De la gelée ?
No, no, thank you, but I do have a favor to ask.
Non, merci, maisj'ai un service a vous demander.
-Name it. -Well, I'm booked to do...
- Allez-y. - Je dois faire
...a children's party tomorrow...
un spectacle pour enfants demain
...and frankly, I don't feel up to it.
etje ne me sens pas d'attaque.
Oh, you're not. You look awful.
Non. Vous avez une mine horrible.
Thank you.
Merci.
Anyway, uh, you know my act better than anybody...
Vous connaissez mon numéro mieux que personne
...l was hoping that maybe you'd fill in for me.
etje me disais que vous pourriez peut-être me remplacer.
Are you saying that you want me to be Professor Proton?
Vous voulez que je sois le professeur Proton ?
-Yeah. -Oh, my.
-Oui. - Mon Dieu!
What an honor. Oh, this is like being asked to...
Quel honneur! C‘est comme sion me demandait
...ascend Mount Olympus and dine with the gods.
de grimper le mont Olympe et de dîner avec les dieux.
Or a Korean family in Alhambra.
Ou avec une famille coréenne a Alhambra.
But they'll know I'm not you.
Mais ils verront que ce n‘est pas vous.
Should I call myself Professor Proton, Jr?
Je m'appellerai Professeur Proton, Jr ?
Sounds great.
Super.
So in a way, it's like I'm your son.
Je suis un peu votre fils.
Whatever.
Si vous voulez.
Father.
Père.
Sure, what the hell.
Au point où j'en suis.
[English - us - an]
[French]